ICICI Lombard is one of the major health
insurance companies in India. Today we will
talk about ICICI Lombard's Health Shield and Health Shield Plus plans.
Hello friends, I am Ashutosh.
Welcome to my YouTube channel. If you want to learn more about
personal finance, please
subscribe to my YouTube channel,
Health Insurance Live.com. If you need any
free consultation related to insurance or mutual funds,
you
can WhatsApp on the number given below. Let's
start the video.
[Music]
ICICI Lombard Health Shield and Health
Shield Plus are both similar
plans. There is very little difference in the features.
So first, let's
talk about their common features and
then we will discuss the difference. The first
feature is in-patient treatment. This means that you will not see any
hospital charges
like room rent
or blood oxygen
theatre charges for more than 24 hours. The
treatment or procedure is completed
but their cost is high. So, these
treatments will also be
covered under this. Next, let's talk about pre-
hospital
medical expenses.  These are
called Priya Hospital Expenses.
In this policy, you
can claim pre-hospitalization expenses for 30 days. This
means that the medical expenses incurred after discharge are covered
under post-hospital expenses.
In this policy,
you can claim medical expenses up to 60 days after discharge.
Talking about post-hospital reset benefit, different companies use different
terms for it, such as
statement automatic recharge. This means that if
a person is hospitalized in the same policy year and the
entire
time gets exhausted, then the
company refills the same time again.
But this reset benefit is not for the
first hospitalization. There is
another
condition in it that the
reset benefit will not be available for meeting the same person.
This means that if a person has
taken hospitalization for a particular disease
and takes hospitalization again for the same disease in the same policy, then the
reset
benefit will not be available for him.
If you have a hospitalization for any other illness, or if
someone else insured under the policy has a
hospitalization, you can avail this reset benefit.
In case of an emergency hospitalization, ambulance charges will also be covered,
for which you can claim 1% of your insurance premium.
If
you take a teleconsultation with a doctor in case of an emergency,
his charges will also be covered. The
next feature is similar to this, which we
know as No Claim Bonus. Every claim-
free company rewards us
in the form of No Claim Bonus, in
which our bonus is increased by 10% every year,
which comes up to a maximum of 50%, then it
reduces in the same proportion,
meaning it will reduce by 10%. The next
feature is free health checkup. The company
gives you coupons twice a year, which you
can redeem against free health checkup by visiting their designated centers. The
next feature is the Balance Program. The
company gives you Balance Points for adopting a healthy lifestyle,
which you can use for
online medical tests and other related services.  You can avail of the free
health checkups you receive.
These wellness points
can be used against outpatient medical expenses.
Features like consultation, medicine and nutrition, and health assistant are
included in your policy,
which are built-in to Health Plus
but not to Health Shield. You
can avail these separately in Shield. The first feature, Claim
Protector, is that
many non-
medical expenses and consumable
charges are not covered in our health insurance, such as syringes, gloves,
etc. What happens is that their
charges can sometimes be up
to 15 to 20% of the claim amount. With this
feature, the expenses related to these non-medical charges are
also covered in our health insurance. This feature is built-in
to Health Plus, but
you can avail it separately in Health Shield. The
next feature is worldwide
coverage. You
can also go to any plant hospital in India or abroad for treatment.
Its healthcare expenses will also be covered, but there is
a condition in this.  There will be a copay application of 10%
for Protector. What happens in this?
Your basic home insurance is
increased according to inflation, which is
linked to the index published by the government or the consumer price index. Apart from this, there
is another difference. In Health and
Health Shield Plus,
you get term options ranging from Rs 5 lakh to Rs 50 lakh.
Apart from these features, there are many other features
which you can avail by paying separate premium with both these plans. The
first
is the bonus, in which apart from crude ASI or
additional home insured, which is your
normal no claim bonus, you
get an extra no claim bonus of 50%
for every claim free year, which will be available up
to a maximum of 100% in policies of Rs 5 and 10 lakh and up
to a maximum of 200% in policies of Rs 15 to 50 lakh. The
second benefit is
of hospital daily gas, in which the
company pays you some
cash payment for hospital stay of more than 3 days, which is a maximum of  It is
available for 10 days. The next benefit is
if you
need the supervision of a nurse for more than 10 days, then the
company pays you up to Rs. 3000 per day for a maximum of
15 days.
Next is compassionate travel. If
you
go for treatment from your native place to some other place, then the charges for your immediate
relatives like spouse, children and
parents to visit you by air are borne by the
company. The next benefit is critical, in which
you are
paid an equal amount if a critical is detected for the first time. The next
benefit is in case of accident, if there is any
accidental case, then the sum
assured is paid to your nominee in case of death. If you have
any doubt, you can ask by commenting below.
If you liked this video, then do
like it so that
we keep getting inspiration to make such informative videos.
Thank you.